<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="historic" ipr="none" docName="9p2000">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
 <front>
  <title abbrev="9P2000">Plan 9 Remote Resource Protocol</title>
  <author initials='E.V.H.' surname="Van Hensbergen" fullname='Eric Van Hensbergen'>
   <organization>
		Plan 9 Fans
	    </organization>
   <address>
    <email>9fans@cse.psu.edu</email>
    <uri>http://plan9.bell-labs.com/plan9</uri>
   </address>
  </author>
  <date month="March" year="2005"/>
  <area>General</area>
  <keyword>Plan 9</keyword>
  <keyword>9P2000</keyword>
  <keyword>9P</keyword>
  <abstract>
   <t>
	9P is a distributed resource sharing protocol developed as
	part of the Plan 9 research operating system at AT&T Bell
	Laboratories (now a part of Lucent Technologies) by the Computer
	Science Research Center.  It can be used to distributed file
	systems, devices, and application services.  It was designed as
	an interface to both local and remote resources, making the
	transition from local to cluster to grid resources transparent.
	</t>
   <t>
	In addition to being supported under Plan 9 and its offspring
	the Inferno operating system, there exists kernel drivers for
	Linux and application libraries supporting other operating
	systems including BSD, OSX, and Solaris.
	</t>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <middle>
  <section title="Requirements notation">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
	    "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
	    and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
	    described in RFC2629"/>.</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
   <t>
   A Plan 9 <xref target="PLAN9" /> server is an agent that provides one or more hierarchical
   file systems -- file trees -- that may be accessed by Plan 9
   processes.	A server  responds  to requests by clients to navigate
   the hierarchy, and to create, remove, read, and write files.	 The
   prototypical server is a separate  machine  that stores large numbers
   of user files on permanent media; such a machine is called, somewhat
   confusingly, a  file	 server.  Another possibility for a server is to
   synthesize files on demand, perhaps based on information on data
   structures  inside  the  kernel;  the proc(3)  kernel  device  is a
   part of the Plan 9 kernel that does this.  User programs can also act
   as servers.
</t>
   <t>
   A connection to a server is a bidirectional communication path from
   the client to the server.  There may be a single client or multiple
   clients sharing the same connection.	 A server's file tree  is
   attached  to	 a process  group's  name  space by bind(2) and mount
   calls; see intro(2).	 Processes in the group are then clients of  the
   server:  system  calls operating on files are translated into
   requests and responses transmitted on the connection to the
   appropriate service.
</t>
   <t>
   The Plan 9 File Protocol, 9P, is used for messages between clients
   and servers.	  A  client transmits requests (T-messages) to a server,
   which subsequently returns replies (R-messages) to the client.  The
   combined acts  of  transmitting  (receiving) a request of a
   particular type, and receiving (transmitting) its reply is  called  a
   transaction	of  that type.
</t>
   <t>
   Each	 message consists of a sequence of bytes.  Two-, four-, and
   eight-byte fields hold unsigned integers represented in  little-
   endian  order (least	 significant  byte  first).   Data  items  of
   larger or variable lengths are represented by a two-byte field
   specifying a count, n, followed  by n bytes of data.	 Text strings
   are represented this way, with the text itself stored as a UTF-8
   encoded sequence of	Unicode characters (see utf(6)).  Text strings
   in 9P messages are not NUL-terminated: n counts the bytes of UTF-8
   data, which include	no  final  zero	 byte.	The  NUL  character is
   illegal in all text strings in 9P, and is therefore excluded from
   file names, user names, and so on.
</t>
   <t>
   Each 9P message begins with	a  four-byte  size  field  specifying
   the length in bytes of the complete message including the four bytes
   of the size field itself.  The next byte is the message type, one of
   the constants  in the enumeration in the include file fcall.h.  The
   next two bytes are an identifying tag, described below.  The
   remaining bytes are parameters of different sizes.  In the message
   descriptions, the number of bytes in a field is given in brackets
   after  the  field  name.   The notation  parameter[n] where n is not
   a constant represents a variable-length parameter: n[2] followed by n
   bytes of data forming the parameter.	 The notation string[s] (using a
   literal s character) is shorthand for s[2] followed by s bytes of
   UTF-8 text.	 (Systems  may	choose	to reduce  the	set  of legal
   characters to reduce syntactic problems, for example to remove
   slashes from name components, but the protocol has no such
   restriction.	  Plan	9  names may contain any printable character
   (that is, any character outside hexadecimal	00-1F  and  80-9F)
   except slash.)   Messages  are  transported	in byte form to allow
   for machine independence; fcall(2) describes routines that convert to
   and from this form into a machine-dependent C structure.
	</t>
   <section anchor="msgs" title="Messages">
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>
      size[4] Tversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tauth tag[2] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rauth tag[2] aqid[13]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Rerror tag[2] ename[s]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tflush tag[2] oldtag[2]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rflush tag[2]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tattach tag[2] fid[4] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rattach tag[2] qid[13]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Twalk tag[2] fid[4] newfid[4] nwname[2] nwname*(wname[s])
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rwalk tag[2] nwqid[2] nwqid*(wqid[13])
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Topen tag[2] fid[4] mode[1]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Ropen tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tcreate tag[2] fid[4] name[s] perm[4] mode[1]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rcreate tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tread tag[2] fid[4] offset[8] count[4]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rread tag[2] count[4] data[count]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Twrite tag[2] fid[4] offset[8] count[4] data[count]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rwrite tag[2] count[4]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tclunk tag[2] fid[4]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rclunk tag[2]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tremove tag[2] fid[4]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rremove tag[2]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tstat tag[2] fid[4]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rstat tag[2] stat[n]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Twstat tag[2] fid[4] stat[n]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rwstat tag[2]
   </t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
   Each T-message has a tag field, chosen and used by the client to
   identify  the  message.   The  reply to the message will have the
   same tag.  Clients must arrange that no two outstanding messages on
   the same connection	have  the same tag.  An exception is the tag
   NOTAG, defined as (ushort)~0 in fcall.h: the client can use	it,
   when	 establishing  a connection, to override tag matching in version
   messages.
</t>
    <t>
   The	type  of  an R-message will either be one greater than the type
   of the corresponding T-message or  Rerror,  indicating  that	 the
   request failed.  In the latter case, the ename field contains a
   string describing the reason for failure.

</t>
    <t>
   The version message identifies the version of the  protocol	and
   indicates  the  maximum  message size the system is prepared to
   handle.  It also initializes the connection and aborts all
   outstanding I/O  on	the connection.	  The  set of messages between
   version requests is called a session.
</t>
    <t>
   Most T-messages contain a fid,  a  32-bit  unsigned	integer	 that
   the client  uses  to	 identify  a ``current file'' on the server.
   Fids are somewhat like file descriptors in a user  process,	but
   they	 are  not restricted  to  files	 open  for I/O: directories
   being examined, files being accessed by stat(2) calls, and so on --
   all files  being manipulated by the operating system -- are
   identified by fids.	Fids are chosen by the client.	All requests on
   a connection	 share	the  same  fid space;  when several clients
   share a connection, the agent managing the sharing must arrange that
   no two clients choose the same fid.
</t>
    <t>
   The fid supplied in an attach message will be taken by  the	server
   to refer  to	 the root of the served file tree.  The attach
   identifies the user to the server and may specify a particular file
   tree served by the server (for those that supply more than one).
</t>
    <t>
   Permission  to  attach  to the service is proven by providing a
   special fid, called afid, in the attach message.  This afid is
   established	by exchanging  auth  messages  and subsequently
   manipulated using read and write messages  to  exchange
   authentication  information	not  defined explicitly	 by  9P <xref target="P9SEC"/>.   Once
   the authentication protocol is complete, the afid is presented in the
   attach to permit the user to access	the service.
</t>
    <t>
   A  walk message causes the server to change the current file
   associated with a fid to be a file in the directory that is the old
   current  file, or  one  of  its subdirectories.  Walk returns a new
   fid that refers to the resulting file.  Usually, a client maintains a
   fid	for  the  root, and navigates by walks from the root fid.
</t>
    <t>
   A  client  can  send multiple T-messages without waiting for the
   corresponding R-messages, but all outstanding T-messages must
   specify different  tags.   The  server  may	delay  the  response to
   a request and respond to later ones; this is sometimes necessary,
   for	example	 when the  client reads from a file that the server
   synthesizes from external events such as keyboard characters.
</t>
    <t>
   Replies (R-messages) to auth, attach, walk, open, and  create
   requests convey a qid field back to the client.  The qid represents
   the server's unique identification for the file being accessed:  two
   files  on  the same	server	hierarchy  are the same if and only if
   their qids are the same.  (The client may have multiple fids pointing
   to a single file  on a  server and hence having a single qid.)  The
   thirteen-byte qid fields hold a one-byte type, specifying  whether
   the	file  is  a  directory, append-only  file, etc., and two
   unsigned integers: first the four-byte qid version, then the eight-
   byte qid path.   The	 path  is  an  integer unique  among  all  files
   in  the hierarchy.  If a file is deleted and recreated with the same
   name in the same directory,	the  old  and  new path components of
   the qids should be different.  The version is a version number for a
   file; typically, it is  incremented	every  time  the file is
   modified.
</t>
    <t>
   An  existing	 file  can  be opened, or a new file may be created in
   the current (directory) file.  I/O of a given number of bytes  at  a
   given offset on an open file is done by read and write.
</t>
    <t>
   A  client  should  clunk  any fid that is no longer needed.	The
   remove transaction deletes files.
</t>
    <t>
   The stat transaction retrieves information about the	 file.	 The
   stat field  in the reply includes the file's name, access permissions
   (read, write and execute for owner, group and public), access and
   modification times,	and  owner  and group identifications (see
   stat(2)).  The owner and group identifications are textual  names.
   The	wstat  transaction allows some of a file's properties to be
   changed.
   A  request can be aborted with a flush request.  When a server
   receives a Tflush, it should not reply to the message with tag oldtag
   (unless it has  already  replied),  and it should immediately send an
   Rflush.  The client must wait until it gets the Rflush (even if  the
   reply  to  the original  message arrives in the interim), at which
   point oldtag may be reused.
</t>
    <t>
   Because the message size is negotiable and some elements of the
   protocol  are  variable length, it is possible (although unlikely) to
   have a situation where a valid message is too large to fit within the
   negotiated size.  For example, a very long file name may cause a
   Rstat of the file or Rread of its directory entry to be too large to
   send.  In  most such	 cases, the server should generate an error
   rather than modify the data to fit, such as by truncating the file
   name.   The	exception  is that  a  long  error string in an Rerror
   message should be truncated if necessary, since the string is only
   advisory and in  some  sense arbitrary.
</t>
    <t>
   Most	 programs  do  not  see the 9P protocol directly; instead calls
   to library routines that access files are translated by the mount
   driver, mnt(3), into 9P messages.
</t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="dirs" title="Directories">
    <t>
   Directories	are  created  by  create with DMDIR set in the
   permissions argument (see stat(5)).	The members of a directory can
   be  found  with read(5).  All directories must support walks to the
   directory ..	 (dot-dot) meaning parent directory, although by
   convention directories contain  no  explicit	 entry	for ..	or .
   (dot).  The parent of the root directory of a server's tree is
   itself.
</t>
    <t>
   Each file server maintains a set of user and group  names.	Each
   user can be a member of any number of groups.  Each group has a group
   leader who has special privileges (see  stat(5)  and	 users(6)).
   Every  file request	has  an implicit user id (copied from the
   original attach) and an implicit set of groups (every group of which
   the user is a  member).
</t>
   </section>
   <section anchor="access" title="Access Permissions">
    <t>
   Each	 file  has an associated owner and group id and three sets of
   permissions: those of  the  owner,  those  of  the  group,  and
   those  of ``other''	users.	 When  the owner attempts to do
   something to a file, the owner, group, and other permissions are
   consulted, and  if  any  of them  grant  the	 requested  permission,
   the operation is allowed.  For someone who is not the owner, but is a
   member of the file's group,	the group  and	other  permissions  are
   consulted.  For everyone else, the other permissions are used.  Each
   set of permissions says whether reading  is	allowed,  whether
   writing is allowed, and whether executing is allowed.  A walk in a
   directory is regarded as executing the directory, not reading it.
   Permissions are kept in the low-order bits of the file mode: owner
   read/write/execute permission represented as 1 in  bits  8, 7,  and
   6  respectively  (using 0 to number the low order).	The group
   permissions are in bits 5, 4, and 3, and the other permissions  are
   in bits 2, 1, and 0.
</t>
    <t>
   The	file  mode contains some additional attributes besides the
   permissions.	 If bit 31 (DMDIR) is set, the file is a directory; if
   bit	30 (DMAPPEND)  is  set,	 the  file  is	append-only  (offset is
   ignored in writes); if bit 29 (DMEXCL) is set, the file is exclusive-
   use (only one client may have it open at a time); if bit 27 (DMAUTH)
   is set, the file is an authentication file established  by  auth
   messages;  if  bit  26 (DMTMP)  is  set,  the  contents  of	the
   file	 (or directory) are not included in nightly archives.  (Bit 28
   is skipped for  historical reasons.)	  These	 bits are reproduced,
   from the top bit down, in the type byte of the Qid: QTDIR, QTAPPEND,
   QTEXCL, (skipping  one  bit)	 QTAUTH, and  QTTMP.   The name QTFILE,
   defined to be zero, identifies the value of the type for a plain
   file.
</t>
   </section>
   <section title="General Definitions">
    <t>
     TODO: Include defintions of general terms used throughout document
  </t>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Protocol Data Types">
   <section title="Basic Data Types">
    <t> TODO: cover how we define data types in our protocol synopsis</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Structured Data Types">
    <t> TODO: cover any structs (like stat) that the protocol uses</t>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title = "Transport and Security Options">
   <section title = "Transport Options">
    <t> TODO: Describe Transport pre-reqs </t>
    <section title = "TCP/IP">
     <t> TODO: describe TCP/IP transport embodiment </t>
    </section>
    <section title = "Function Call">
     <t> TODO: describe function call embodiment </t>
    </section>
    <section title = "Pipe">
     <t> TODO: describe pipe embodiment </t>
    </section>
    <section title = "Shared Memory">
     <t> TODO: describe shared memory embodiment</t>
    </section>
   </section>
   <section title = "Security">
    <section title = "Plan 9 Authentication Model">
     <t>TODO: describe Plan 9 Authentication Model</t>
    </section>
    <section title = "u9fs rhosts model">
     <t>TODO: describe rhosts model</t>
    </section>
    <section title = "Challenge/Response model">
     <t>TODO: describe u9fs challenge/response model</t>
    </section>
    <section title = "noauth">
     <t>TODO: describe noauth model</t>
    </section>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title = "File Handles">
   <t>TODO: describe FIDs in some detail</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "File Attributes">
   <t>TODO: describe stat in some detail - perhaps steal from protocol section</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Namespace">
   <t>TODO: describe Plan 9 dynamic namespace and how it relates to 9P</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Locking">
   <t>TODO: describe Plan 9 locking semantics (OEXCL)</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Client-Side Caching">
   <t>TODO: describe Plan 9 cache semantics and limitations (ref. cfs)</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Versioning">
   <t>TODO: describe protocol versioning in detail (steal from Protocol section)</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Internationalization">
   <t>TODO: describe 9P rune support</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Error Definitions">
   <t>TODO: enumerate standard file system error strings and describe possibility
    of application error strings</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="protocol" title="Protocol Operations">
   <section anchor="version" title="version - negotiate protocol version">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>size[4] Tversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]</t>
      <t>size[4] Rversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>
       The version request negotiates the protocol version and message size to
       be used on the connection  and  initializes  the	 connection  for  I/O.
       Tversion	 must  be the first message sent on the 9P connection, and the
       client cannot issue any further requests	 until	it  has	 received  the
       Rversion	 reply.	 The tag should be NOTAG (value (ushort)~0) for a ver-
       sion message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       The client suggests a maximum message size, msize, that is the  maximum
       length,	in bytes, it will ever generate or expect to receive in a sin-
       gle 9P message.	This count includes all	 9P  protocol  data,  starting
       from  the  size	field  and extending through the message, but excludes
       enveloping transport protocols.	The server responds with its own maxi-
       mum,  msize,  which  must  be less than or equal to the client's value.
       Thenceforth, both sides of the connection must honor this limit.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>

       The version string identifies the level of the  protocol.   The	string
       must  always  begin with the two characters ``9P''.  If the server does
       not understand the client's version string, it should respond  with  an
       Rversion	 message (not Rerror) with the version string the 7 characters
       ``unknown''.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>

       The server may respond with the client's version string, or  a  version
       string identifying an earlier defined protocol version.	Currently, the
       only defined version is the 6 characters ``9P2000''.   Version  strings
       are defined such that, if the client string contains one or more period
       characters, the initial substring up to but not	including  any	single
       period  in the version string defines a version of the protocol.	 After
       stripping any such period-separated suffix, the server  is  allowed  to
       respond	with  a	 string of the form 9Pnnnn, where nnnn is less than or
       equal to the digits sent by the client.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>

       The client and server will use the  protocol  version  defined  by  the
       server's response for all subsequent communication on the connection.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>

       A successful version request initializes the connection.	 All outstand-
       ing I/O on the  connection  is  aborted;	 all  active  fids  are	 freed
       (`clunked')   automatically.   The  set	of  messages  between  version
       requests is called a session.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>ENTRY POINTS</t>
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>
       The version message is generated by the fversion system	call.	It  is
       also  generated	automatically, if required, by a mount or fauth system
       call on an uninitialized connection.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="attach, auth - messages to establish a connection">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       size[4] Tauth tag[2] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
</t>
      <t>
       size[4] Rauth tag[2] aqid[13]
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       size[4] Tattach tag[2] fid[4] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
</t>
      <t>
	size[4] Rattach tag[2] qid[13]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       The  attach  message  serves as a fresh introduction from a user on the
       client machine to the server.  The message identifies the user  (uname)
       and  may	 select	 the  file  tree to access (aname).  The afid argument
       specifies a fid previously established by an auth message, as described
       below.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       As  a  result of the attach transaction, the client will have a connec-
       tion to the root directory of the desired  file	tree,  represented  by
       fid.  An error is returned if fid is already in use.  The server's idea
       of the root of the file tree is represented by the returned qid.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       If the client does not wish to authenticate the	connection,  or	 knows
       that  authentication is not required, the afid field in the attach mes-
       sage should be set to NOFID, defined as (u32int)~0  in  fcall.h.	  If
       the  client  does wish to authenticate, it must acquire and validate an
       afid using an auth message before doing the attach.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       The auth message contains afid, a new fid to be established for authen-
       tication,  and  the uname and aname that will be those of the following
       attach message.	If the server  does  not  require  authentication,  it
       returns Rerror to the Tauth message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       If  the	server does require authentication, it returns aqid defining a
       file of type QTAUTH (see intro(5)) that may be read and written	(using
       read  and write messages in the usual way) to execute an authentication
       protocol.  That protocol's definition is not part of 9P itself.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       Once the protocol is complete, the same afid is presented in the attach
       message	for  the user, granting entry.	The same validated afid may be
       used for multiple attach messages with the same uname and aname.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       An attach  transaction  will  be	 generated  for	 kernel	 devices  (see
       intro(3))  when	a  system  call	 evaluates  a file name beginning with
       Pipe(2) generates an attach on the kernel device	 pipe(3).   The	 mount
       system  call  (see  bind(2))  generates an attach message to the remote
       file server.  When the kernel boots, an attach  is  made	 to  the  root
       device,	root(3),  and  then  an	 attach	 is made to the requested file
       server machine.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       An auth transaction is generated by the fauth(2) system call or by  the
       first mount system call on an uninitialized connection.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
SEE ALSO
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       auth(2), fauth(2), version(5), authsrv(6)
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="clunk - forget about a fid">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       size[4] Tclunk tag[2] fid[4]
</t>
      <t>
	size[4] Rclunk tag[2]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       The  clunk request informs the file server that the current file repre-
       sented by fid is no longer needed by the client.	 The  actual  file  is
       not  removed on the server unless the fid had been opened with ORCLOSE.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       Once a fid has been clunked, the same fid can be reused in a  new  walk
       or attach request.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       Even if the clunk returns an error, the fid is no longer valid.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       A  clunk	 message is generated by close and indirectly by other actions
       such as failed open calls.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="error - return an error">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       size[4] Rerror tag[2] ename[s]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       The  Rerror  message  (there  is	 no Terror) is used to return an error
       string describing the failure of a transaction.	It replaces the corre-
       sponding	 reply message that would accompany a successful call; its tag
       is that of the failing request.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
       By convention, clients  may  truncate  error  messages  after  ERRMAX-1
       bytes; ERRMAX is defined in libc.h.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="flush - abort a message">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tflush tag[2] oldtag[2]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rflush tag[2]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          When the response to a request is no longer needed, such as
          when a user interrupts a process doing a read(2), a Tflush
          request is sent to the server to purge the pending response.
          The message being flushed is identified by oldtag. The
          semantics of flush depends on messages arriving in order.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The server should answer the flush message immediately.  If
          it recognizes oldtag as the tag of a pending transaction, it
          should abort any pending response and discard that tag.  In
          either case, it should respond with an Rflush echoing the
          tag (not oldtag) of the Tflush message.  A Tflush can never
          be responded to by an Rerror message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The server may respond to the pending request before
          responding to the Tflush.  It is possible for a client to
          send multiple Tflush messages for a particular pending
          request.  Each subsequent Tflush must contain as oldtag the
          tag of the pending request (not a previous Tflush).  Should
          multiple Tflushes be received for a pending request, they
          must be answered in order.  A Rflush for any of the multiple
          Tflushes implies an answer for all previous ones.  There-
          fore, should a server receive a request and then multiple
          flushes for that request, it need respond only to the last
          flush.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          When the client sends a Tflush, it must wait to receive the
          corresponding Rflush before reusing oldtag for subsequent
          messages.  If a response to the flushed request is received
          before the Rflush, the client must honor the response as if
          it had not been flushed, since the completed request may
          signify a state change in the server.  For instance, Tcreate
          may have created a file and Twalk may have allocated a fid.
          If no response is received before the Rflush, the flushed
          transaction is considered to have been canceled, and should
          be treated as though it had never been sent.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Several exceptional conditions are handled correctly by the
          above specification: sending multiple flushes for a single
          tag, flushing after a transaction is completed, flushing a
          Tflush, and flushing an invalid tag.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="open, create - prepare a fid for I/O on an existing or new file">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Topen tag[2] fid[4] mode[1]
 </t>
      <t>
         size[4] Ropen tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          size[4] Tcreate tag[2] fid[4] name[s] perm[4] mode[1]
   </t>
      <t>
        size[4] Rcreate tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          The open request asks the file server to check permissions
          and prepare a fid for I/O with subsequent read and write
          messages.  The mode field determines the type of I/O: 0
          (called OREAD in libc.h), 1 (OWRITE), 2 (ORDWR), and 3
          (OEXEC) mean read access, write access, read and write
          access, and execute access, to be checked against the per-
          missions for the file.  In addition, if mode has the OTRUNC
          (0x10) bit set, the file is to be truncated, which requires
          write permission (if the file is append-only, and permission
          is granted, the open succeeds but the file will not be trun-
          cated); if the mode has the ORCLOSE (0x40) bit set, the file
          is to be removed when the fid is clunked, which requires
          permission to remove the file from its directory.  All other
          bits in mode should be zero.  It is illegal to write a
          directory, truncate it, or attempt to remove it on close.
          If the file is marked for exclusive use (see stat(5)), only
          one client can have the file open at any time.  That is,
          after such a file has been opened, further opens will fail
          until fid has been clunked.  All these permissions are
          checked at the time of the open request; subsequent changes
          to the permissions of files do not affect the ability to
          read, write, or remove an open file.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The create request asks the file server to create a new file
          with the name supplied, in the directory (dir) represented
          by fid, and requires write permission in the directory.  The
          owner of the file is the implied user id of the request, the
          group of the file is the same as dir, and the permissions
          are the value of
</t>
      <t>
       <list>
        <t>
                    perm & (~0666 | (dir.perm & 0666))
</t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          if a regular file is being created and
</t>
      <t>
       <list>
        <t>
                    perm & (~0777 | (dir.perm & 0777))
</t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          if a directory is being created.  This means, for example,
          that if the create allows read permission to others, but the
          containing directory does not, then the created file will
          not allow others to read the file.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Finally, the newly created file is opened according to mode,
          and fid will represent the newly opened file.  Mode is not
          checked against the permissions in perm. The qid for the new
          file is returned with the create reply message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Directories are created by setting the DMDIR bit
          (0x80000000) in the perm.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The names . and .. are special; it is illegal to create
          files with these names.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          It is an error for either of these messages if the fid is
          already the product of a successful open or create message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          An attempt to create a file in a directory where the given
          name already exists will be rejected; in this case, the
          create system call (see open(2)) uses open with truncation.
          The algorithm used by the create system call is: first walk
          to the directory to contain the file.  If that fails, return
          an error.  Next walk to the specified file.  If the walk
          succeeds, send a request to open and truncate the file and
          return the result, successful or not.  If the walk fails,
          send a create message.  If that fails, it may be because the
          file was created by another process after the previous walk
          failed, so (once) try the walk and open again.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          For the behavior of create on a union directory, see
          bind(2).
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The iounit field returned by open and create may be zero.
          If it is not, it is the maximum number of bytes that are
          guaranteed to be read from or written to the file without
          breaking the I/O transfer into multiple 9P messages; see
          read(5).
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          Open and create both generate open messages; only create
          generates a create message.  The iounit associated with an
          open file may be discovered by calling iounit(2).
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          For programs that need atomic file creation, without the
          race that exists in the open-create sequence described
          above, the kernel does the following.  If the OEXCL (0x1000)
          bit is set in the mode for a create system call, the open
          message is not sent; the kernel issues only the create.
          Thus, if the file exists, create will draw an error, but if
          it doesn't and the create system call succeeds, the process
          issuing the create is guaranteed to be the one that created
          the file.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="read, write - transfer data from and to a file">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tread tag[2] fid[4] offset[8] count[4]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rread tag[2] count[4] data[count]
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          size[4] Twrite tag[2] fid[4] offset[8] count[4] data[count]
 </t>
      <t>  
       size[4] Rwrite tag[2] count[4]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          The read request asks for count bytes of data from the file
          identified by fid, which must be opened for reading, start-
          ing offset bytes after the beginning of the file.  The bytes
          are returned with the read reply message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The count field in the reply indicates the number of bytes
          returned.  This may be less than the requested amount.  If
          the offset field is greater than or equal to the number of
          bytes in the file, a count of zero will be returned.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          For directories, read returns an integral number of direc-
          tory entries exactly as in stat (see stat(5)), one for each
          member of the directory.  The read request message must have
          offset equal to zero or the value of offset in the previous
          read on the directory, plus the number of bytes returned in
          the previous read.  In other words, seeking other than to
          the beginning is illegal in a directory (see seek(2)).
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The write request asks that count bytes of data be recorded
          in the file identified by fid, which must be opened for
          writing, starting offset bytes after the beginning of the
          file.  If the file is append-only, the data will be placed
          at the end of the file regardless of offset. Directories may
          not be written.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The write reply records the number of bytes actually writ-
          ten.  It is usually an error if this is not the same as
          requested.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Because 9P implementations may limit the size of individual
          messages, more than one message may be produced by a single
          read or write call.  The iounit field returned by open(5),
          if non-zero, reports the maximum size that is guaranteed to
          be transferred atomically.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          Read and write messages are generated by the corresponding
          calls.  Because they include an offset, the pread and pwrite
          calls correspond more directly to the 9P messages.  Although
          seek(2) affects the offset, it does not generate a message.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="remove - remove a file from a server">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tremove tag[2] fid[4]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rremove tag[2]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          The remove request asks the file server both to remove the
          file represented by fid and to clunk the fid, even if the
          remove fails.  This request will fail if the client does not
          have write permission in the parent directory.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          It is correct to consider remove to be a clunk with the side
          effect of removing the file if permissions allow.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          If a file has been opened as multiple fids, possibly on dif-
          ferent connections, and one fid is used to remove the file,
          whether the other fids continue to provide access to the
          file is implementation-defined.  The Plan 9 file servers
          (like fs(4)) remove the file immediately: attempts to use
          the other fids will yield a ``phase error.''  U9fs(4) fol-
          lows the semantics of the underlying Unix file system, so
          other fids typically remain usable.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          Remove messages are generated by remove.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="stat, wstat - inquire or change file attributes">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tstat tag[2] fid[4]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rstat tag[2] stat[n]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Twstat tag[2] fid[4] stat[n]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rwstat tag[2]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          The stat transaction inquires about the file identified by
          fid. The reply will contain a machine-independent directory
          entry, stat, laid out as follows:
</t>
      <t>
       <list>
        <t>
         <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="size[2]">
           <vspace/>
               total byte count of the following data
</t>
          <t hangText="type[2]">
           <vspace/>
               for kernel use
</t>
          <t hangText="dev[4]">
           <vspace/>
               for kernel use
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.type[1]">
           <vspace/>
               the type of the file (directory, etc.), represented as
               a bit vector corresponding to the high 8 bits of the
               file's mode word.
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.vers[4]">
           <vspace/>
               version number for given path
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.path[8]">
           <vspace/>
               the file server's unique identification for the file
</t>
          <t hangText="mode[4]">
           <vspace/>
               permissions and flags
</t>
          <t hangText="atime[4]">
           <vspace/>
               last access time
</t>
          <t hangText="mtime[4]">
           <vspace/>
               last modification time
</t>
          <t hangText="length[8]">
           <vspace/>
               length of file in bytes
</t>
          <t hangText="name[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               file name; must be / if the file is the root directory
               of the server
</t>
          <t hangText="uid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               owner name
</t>
          <t hangText="gid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               group name
</t>
          <t hangText="muid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               name of the user who last modified the file
</t>
         </list>
        </t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Integers in this encoding are in little-endian order (least
          significant byte first).  The convM2D and convD2M routines
          (see fcall(2)) convert between directory entries and a C
          structure called a Dir.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The mode contains permission bits as described in intro(5)
          and the following: 0x80000000 (DMDIR, this file is a direc-
          tory), 0x40000000 (DMAPPEND, append only), 0x20000000
          (DMEXCL, exclusive use), 0x04000000 (DMTMP, temporary);
          these are echoed in Qid.type.  Writes to append-only files
          always place their data at the end of the file; the offset
          in the write message is ignored, as is the OTRUNC bit in an
          open.  Exclusive use files may be open for I/O by only one
          fid at a time across all clients of the server.  If a second
          open is attempted, it draws an error.  Servers may implement
          a timeout on the lock on an exclusive use file: if the fid
          holding the file open has been unused for an extended period
          (of order at least minutes), it is reasonable to break the
          lock and deny the initial fid further I/O.  Temporary files
          are not included in nightly archives (see fossil(4)).
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The two time fields are measured in seconds since the epoch
          (Jan 1 00:00 1970 GMT).  The mtime field reflects the time
          of the last change of content (except when later changed by
          wstat).  For a plain file, mtime is the time of the most
          recent create, open with truncation, or write; for a direc-
          tory it is the time of the most recent remove, create, or
          wstat of a file in the directory.  Similarly, the atime
          field records the last read of the contents; also it is set
          whenever mtime is set.  In addition, for a directory, it is
          set by an attach, walk, or create, all whether successful or
          not.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The muid field names the user whose actions most recently
          changed the mtime of the file.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The length records the number of bytes in the file.  Direc-
          tories and most files representing devices have a conven-
          tional length of 0.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The stat request requires no special permissions.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The wstat request can change some of the file status
          information.  The name can be changed by anyone with write
          permission in the parent directory; it is an error to change
          the name to that of an existing file.  The length can be
          changed (affecting the actual length of the file) by anyone
          with write permission on the file.  It is an error to
          attempt to set the length of a directory to a non-zero
          value, and servers may decide to reject length changes for
          other reasons.  The mode and mtime can be changed by the
          owner of the file or the group leader of the file's current
          group.  The directory bit cannot be changed by a wstat; the
          other defined permission and mode bits can.  The gid can be
          changed: by the owner if also a member of the new group; or
          by the group leader of the file's current group if also
          leader of the new group (see intro(5) for more information
          about permissions and users(6) for users and groups).  None
          of the other data can be altered by a wstat and attempts to
          change them will trigger an error.  In particular, it is
          illegal to attempt to change the owner of a file.  (These
          conditions may be relaxed when establishing the initial
          state of a file server; see fsconfig(8).)
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Either all the changes in wstat request happen, or none of
          them does: if the request succeeds, all changes were made;
          if it fails, none were.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          A wstat request can avoid modifying some properties of the
          file by providing explicit ``don't touch'' values in the
          stat data that is sent: zero-length strings for text values
          and the maximum unsigned value of appropriate size for inte-
          gral values.  As a special case, if all the elements of the
          directory entry in a Twstat message are ``don't touch'' val-
          ues, the server may interpret it as a request to guarantee
          that the contents of the associated file are committed to
          stable storage before the Rwstat message is returned.  (Con-
          sider the message to mean, ``make the state of the file
          exactly what it claims to be.'')
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          A read of a directory yields an integral number of directory
          entries in the machine independent encoding given above (see
          read(5)).
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Note that since the stat information is sent as a 9P
          variable-length datum, it is limited to a maximum of 65535
          bytes.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          Stat messages are generated by fstat and stat.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          Wstat messages are generated by fwstat and wstat.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     BUGS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          To make the contents of a directory, such as returned by
          read(5), easy to parse, each directory entry begins with a
          size field.  For consistency, the entries in Twstat and
          Rstat messages also contain their size, which means the size
          appears twice.  For example, the Rstat message is formatted
          as ``(4+1+2+2+n)[4] Rstat tag[2] n[2] (n-2)[2] type[2]
          dev[4]...,'' where n is the value returned by convD2M.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   <section title="walk - descend a directory hierarchy">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Twalk tag[2] fid[4] newfid[4] nwname[2] nwname*(wname[s])
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rwalk tag[2] nwqid[2] nwqid*(qid[13])
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          The walk request carries as arguments an existing fid and a
          proposed newfid (which must not be in use unless it is the
          same as fid) that the client wishes to associate with the
          result of traversing the directory hierarchy by `walking'
          the hierarchy using the successive path name elements wname.
          The fid must represent a directory unless zero path name
          elements are specified.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The fid must be valid in the current session and must not
          have been opened for I/O by an open or create message.  If
          the full sequence of nwname elements is walked successfully,
          newfid will represent the file that results.  If not, newfid
          (and fid) will be unaffected.  However, if newfid is in use
          or otherwise illegal, an Rerror is returned.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The name ``..''  (dot-dot) represents the parent directory.
          The name ``.''  (dot), meaning the current directory, is not
          used in the protocol.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          It is legal for nwname to be zero, in which case newfid will
          represent the same file as fid and the walk will usually
          succeed; this is equivalent to walking to dot.  The rest of
          this discussion assumes nwname is greater than zero.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          The nwname path name elements wname are walked in order,
          ``elementwise''.  For the first elementwise walk to succeed,
          the file identified by fid must be a directory, and the
          implied user of the request must have permission to search
          the directory (see intro(5)). Subsequent elementwise walks
          have equivalent restrictions applied to the implicit fid
          that results from the preceding elementwise walk.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          If the first element cannot be walked for any reason, Rerror
          is returned.  Otherwise, the walk will return an Rwalk mes-
          sage containing nwqid qids corresponding, in order, to the
          files that are visited by the nwqid successful elementwise
          walks; nwqid is therefore either nwname or the index of the
          first elementwise walk that failed.  The value of nwqid can-
          not be zero unless nwname is zero.  Also, nwqid will always
          be less than or equal to nwname.  Only if it is equal, how-
          ever, will newfid be affected, in which case newfid will
          represent the file reached by the final elementwise walk
          requested in the message.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          A walk of the name ``..''  in the root directory of a server
          is equivalent to a walk with no name elements.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          If newfid is the same as fid, the above discussion applies,
          with the obvious difference that if the walk changes the
          state of newfid, it also changes the state of fid; and if
          newfid is unaffected, then fid is also unaffected.
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
          To simplify the implementation of the servers, a maximum of
          sixteen name elements or qids may be packed in a single mes-
          sage.  This constant is called MAXWELEM in fcall(2). Despite
          this restriction, the system imposes no limit on the number
          of elements in a file name, only the number that may be
          transmitted in a single message.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     ENTRY POINTS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          A call to chdir(2) causes a walk.  One or more walk messages
          may be generated by any of the following calls, which evalu-
          ate file names: bind, create, exec, mount, open, remove,
          stat, unmount, wstat. The file name element . (dot) is
          interpreted locally and is not transmitted in walk messages.
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>Plenty.  For now see the Security in Plan 9
		<xref target="P9SEC"/> paper.  This information will
		be incorperated into this document or a related
		RFC by-and-by.</t>
  </section>
  <section title="IANA Considerationos">
   <t>TODO: figure out if we have to do anything here</t>
   <t> we need to specify the numeric form of protocol operations somewhere</t>
  </section>
  <section title="Protocol Definitions">
   <t>TODO: inspired by NFSv4 - embed protocol include files</t>
  </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
  <references title='Normative References'>
		<reference anchor="PLAN9" target="http://plan9.bell-labs.com/plan9">
    <front>
     <title>Plan 9 Home Page</title>
     <author initials="" surname="Lucent Technologies" fullname="Lucent Technolgoies">
      <organization/>
     </author>
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="P9SEC" target="http://plan9.bell-labs.com/sys/doc/auth.html">
    <front>
     <title>Security in Plan 9</title>
     <author initials="R.C." surname="Cox" fullname="Russ Cox">
      <organization>
				MIT LCS
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="E.G." surname="Grosse" fullname="Eric Grosse">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="R.P." surname="Pike" fullname="Rob Pike">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="D.P." surname="Presotto" fullname="Dave Presotto">
      <organization>
				Avaya Labs and Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="S.Q." surname="Quinlan" fullname="Sean Quinlan">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <date year="2002" />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="Proceedings" value="of the Usenix Security Symposium" />
   </reference>
  </references>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>
This protocol was the result of work done by the Computing Science
Research Center of AT&T Bell Labs (now a part of Lucent Technologies) and in
particular:
<list>
     <t>
Rob Pike</t>
     <t>
Dave Presotto</t>
     <t>
Ken Thompson</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Copyright">
   <t>
  This specification is derrived from the Plan 9 Documentation and Manual Pages.
  The source material is
  Copyright (C) 2003, Lucent Technologies Inc.  and others.  All Rights Reserved.
  </t>
   <t>
  Extensions to the original source material are Copyright (C) 2005, the authors
  of this document (as specified in Authors List in the References section).
  </t>
  </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
