<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- edited with XMLSPY v5 rel. 3 U (http://www.xmlspy.com)
     by Daniel M Kohn (private) -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<rfc category="exp" ipr="none" 
docName="experimental-draft-9P2000-unix-extension"
updates="experimental-draft-9P2000-protocol">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no" ?>
 <front>
  <title abbrev="9P2000.u">Plan 9 Remote Resource Protocol Unix Extension</title>
  <author initials='E.V.H.' surname="Van Hensbergen" fullname='Eric Van Hensbergen'>
   <organization>
		Plan 9 Fans
	    </organization>
   <address>
    <email>9fans@cse.psu.edu</email>
    <uri>http://plan9.bell-labs.com/plan9</uri>
   </address>
  </author>
  <date month="August" year="2009"/>
  <area>General</area>
  <keyword>Plan 9</keyword>
  <keyword>9P2000</keyword>
  <keyword>9P2000.u</keyword>
  <keyword>v9fs</keyword>
  <keyword>9P</keyword>
  <abstract>
   <t>
	9P is a distributed resource sharing protocol developed as
	part of the Plan 9 research operating system at AT&T Bell
	Laboratories (now a part of Lucent Technologies) by the Computer
	Science Research Center.  It can be used to distributed file
	systems, devices, and application services.  It was designed as
	an interface to both local and remote resources, making the
	transition from local to cluster to grid resources transparent.
	</t>
   <t>
   	9P2000.u is a set of extensions to the 9P protocol to better
	support UNIX environments connecting to Plan 9 file servers and
	UNIX environments connecting to other UNIX environments.  The
	extensions include support for symbolic links, additional modes,
	and special files (such as pipes and devices).  Also included
	are hints to better support mapping of numeric user-ids, group-ids, 
	and error codes.
	</t>
  </abstract>
 </front>
 <middle>
  <section title="Requirements notation">
   <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
	    "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY",
	    and "OPTIONAL" in this document are to be interpreted as
	    described in RFC2119.</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
<t>
Many modern UNIX systems, including Linux use a virtual file system (VFS) 
layer as a basic level of abstraction for accessing underlying 
implementations. Implementing 9P2000 under Linux is a matter of mapping VFS 
operations to their associated 9P operations. The problem, however, is that 
9P2000 was designed for a non-UNIX system so there are several fundamental 
differences in the functional semantics provided by 9P.
</t>
<t>
To preserve compatibility with these pre-existing features we propose 
a transparent extension to the file system semantics which minimally effects 
the protocol syntax.  9P2000.u is a dialect of 9P2000 negotiated in the 
Tversion/Rversion exchange.  If the server agrees to 9P2000.u, then the wire 
protocol that follows is 9P2000 with these changes.
</t>
<section title="Overview of Differences">
<section title="Numeric Versus String IDs">
<t>
Under Plan 9 <xref target="PLAN9" />, user names as well as groups are represented by strings, while 
on Unix they are represented by unique numbers. This is complicated by Linux 
making it exceedingly difficult to map these numeric identifiers to their 
string values in the kernel. Many of the available UNIX network file systems 
avoid this issue and simply use numeric identifiers over the wire, hoping they 
map to the remote system. NFSv4 has provisions for sending string group 
and user info over the wire and then contacting a user-space daemon which 
attempts to provide a valid mapping.
</t>
<t>
9P2000.u provides a dual approach to this problem, changes have been made
to the protocol to allow for numeric identifiers to be used along-side
strings.  Servers should make every attempt to provide valid information
for both the numeric and string form of identifiers.  Clients can then use
the available information to best map the identifiers to their local
environment.  Use of extended form string user names (e.g. user@domain)
as specified in the NFSv4 environment is also valid.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Error Strings Versus Error Codes">
<t>
A similar problem exists for error numbers, by default VFS operations 
return error numbers, whereas Plan 9 (and 9P) use error strings to 
describe failure conditions.  This problem is further exacerbated by 
the potential for Plan 9 synthetic file servers to return custom error
strings which may not match any pre-defined set (or pattern) of 
standard error messages.
</t>
<t>
Again, our approach is to provide as much information as possible in
order to help clients properly convey error conditions to end-applications
and end-users.  As such both error strings and error codes are conveyed in
the 9P2000.u version of the protocol.  A suggested implementation is that
non-standard/unrecognized error strings/codes be made available to
applications via some mechanism in order to communicate application
synthetic file system events (via sysfs or procfs in Linux, or perhaps
via a special extended attribute).
</t>
</section>
<section title="Permission Modes">
<t>
Plan 9 has a different user security model <xref target="P9SEC"/>, so there 
is no such concept as set-uid or set-gid permissions.  There is also no 
equivalent for the sticky bit.  Luckily, Plan 9 has plenty of space in 
higher permission mode bit space for such extensions.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Special Files and Links">
<t>
One of the unique aspects of the Plan 9 name space is that it is dynamic. 
Users are able to bind files and directories over each other in stackable 
layers similar to union file systems. This aspect of Plan 9 name spaces has 
obviated the need for symbolic or hard links. Symlinks on a remote UNIX file 
server will be traversed transparently as part of a walk - there is no native 
ability within Plan 9 to create symlinks. This breaks many assumptions for 
Linux file-systems and many existing applications (for example the kernel 
build creates a symlink in the include directory as part of the make process).
</t>
<t>
Another unique aspect is that named pipes and devices look just like other
files in Plan 9, there are no special mode bits and no concept of major
and minor block numbers.
</t>
<t>
To solve both of these problems special mode bits are introduced to mark
special file types and a variable-length string field is added to the
file attribute structure which is used to store the additional information
associated with these special files.  In the case of symlinks, for instance,
the variable length string contains the full path target of the symbolic
link.
</t>
</section>
<section title="ioctl">
<t>
A VFS function not accounted for in the 9P infrastructure is the ioctl
command.  No attempt has been made at this time to accomodate its
functionality.  Plan 9 has traditionally used elements within a synthetic
file system to provide for similar functionality, with the added benefit of
getting transparent network distribution of the control path.  For such
devices/files that still require the use of ioctl, gateway synthetic file
systems are suggested to provide analogous functionality.
</t>
</section>
<section title="Extended Attributes">
<t>
A relatively recent addition to VFS interfaces is the ability to have
arbitrary key/value pairs added to file meta-data.  9P2000.u doesn't
have provisions to accomodate this feature, but it may be added in the
future as more file systems adopt extended attributes.
</t>
</section>
</section>
   <section anchor="msgs" title="Changed Messages">
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>
      size[4] Tversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Rerror tag[2] ename[s] errno[4]
   </t>
<t>
<vspace/>
size[4] Tauth tag[2] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
</t>
<t>
size[4] Rauth tag[2] aqid[13]
</t>
<t>
<vspace/>
size[4] Tattach tag[2] fid[4] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s]
</t>
<t>
size[4] Rattach tag[2] qid[13]
</t>
<t>
<vspace/>
size[4] Tcreate tag[2] fid[4] name[s] perm[4] mode[1] extension[s]
</t>
<t>
size[4] Rcreate tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
</t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Tstat tag[2] fid[4]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rstat tag[2] stat[n]
   </t>
      <t>
       <vspace/>
      size[4] Twstat tag[2] fid[4] stat[n]
   </t>
      <t>
      size[4] Rwstat tag[2]
   </t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title="Protocol Data Types">
   <section title="Changed Basic Data Types">
    <t> TODO: cover changed data types in our protocol synopsis</t>
   </section>
   <section title="Changed Structured Data Types">
    <t> TODO: cover changed structs (like stat) that the protocol uses</t>
   </section>
  </section>
  <section title = "Changed File Attributes">
   <t>TODO: discuss changes</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Versioning">
   <t>TODO: describe protocol versioning in detail (steal from Protocol section)</t>
  </section>
  <section title = "Error Definitions">
   <t>TODO: enumerate new standard file system error strings and describe 
   possibility of application error strings</t>
  </section>
  <section anchor="protocol" title="Changed Protocol Operations">
   <section anchor="version" title="version - negotiate protocol version">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>size[4] Tversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]</t>
      <t>size[4] Rversion tag[2] msize[4] version[s]</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list style="empty">
      <t>
	Support for 9P2000.u is an optional extension which isn't
	quite covered in the existing version semantics for 9P2000.
	The original protocol specification describes discarding
	anything after an initial period in the version string.  We
	use the information following the period as a method for
	negotiating optional protocol extensions.
     </t>
     <t><vspace/>
	If a client desires support for the UNIX extensions, it will
	send the add a .u to the end of the version string (e.g. 9P2000.u).
	If a server is capable of supporting the extension, it will
	return 9P2000.u back to the client.  If the server is incapable
	or unwilling to support the extensions, it will return the
	version string without the extension specification (e.g. 9P2000).
     </t>
     <t><vspace/>
	Clients should be implemented in such a way to be able to operate
	without the extensions in some degraded form of operation.  
	Specifics for how to gracefully degrade operation without 
	specific extensions are suggested by this document.
     </t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>

<section title="error - return an error">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
       size[4] Rerror tag[2] ename[s] errno[4]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
	An errno field has been added to the message in order to provide
	a hint of the underlying UNIX error number which caused the error
	on the server.  Due to consistency problems of mapping error
	numbers betweeen different versions of UNIX, clients should give
	preference to the error string in attempting to report the error,
	however, in the event that they are unable to map an error string,
	they may return the errno to the application.
      </t>
      <t><vspace/>
	A special errno (ERRUNDEF) is returned by servers who do not wish
	to return raw error numbers.  In the event that clients can not 
	interpret the error string, they should somehow make the error
	string available to end-application/end-user via dynamic custom
	error codes.
      </t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>

<section title="auth/attach - messages to establish a connection">
    <t>
SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
       <t>size[4] Tattach tag[2] fid[4] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s] n_uname[4]</t>
       <t>size[4] Rattach tag[2] qid[13]</t>
       <t>size[4] Tauth tag[2] afid[4] uname[s] aname[s] n_uname[4]</t>
       <t>size[4] Rauth tag[2] aqid[13]</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
	A numeric uname field has been added to the attach and auth messages
	in order to provide hints to map a string to a numeric id if such
	a facility is not available.
	
	The numeric uname should be given preference over the uname string
	unless n_uname is unspecified (~0).
      </t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>
   
<section title="open, create - prepare a fid for I/O on an existing or new file">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tcreate tag[2] fid[4] name[s] perm[4] mode[1] extension[s]
   </t>
      <t>
        size[4] Rcreate tag[2] qid[13] iounit[4]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
      The most signifigant change to the create operation is the new
      permission modes which allow for creation of special files.
      In addition to creating directories with DMDIR, 9P2000.u allows
      the creation of symlinks (DMSYMLINK), devices (DMDEVICE), 
      named pipes (DMNAMEPIPE), and sockets (DMSOCKET). extension[s] 
      is a string describing special files, depending on the mode bit. 
      For DSYMLINK files, the string is the target of the link. For 
      DMDEVICE files, the string is "b 1 2" for a block device with 
      major 1, minor 2. For normal files, this string is empty.
     </t>
     </list>
    </t>
   </section>

<section title="stat, wstat - inquire or change file attributes">
    <t>
     SYNOPSIS
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
          size[4] Tstat tag[2] fid[4]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rstat tag[2] stat[n]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Twstat tag[2] fid[4] stat[n]
</t>
      <t>
          size[4] Rwstat tag[2]
</t>
     </list>
    </t>
    <t>
     DESCRIPTION
</t>
    <t>
     <list>
      <t>
	There are four new fields in the stat structure supporting
	9P2000 extensions - as well as new qid.type
	bits and mode bits.
</t>
      <t>
       <list>
        <t>
         <list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="size[2]">
           <vspace/>
               total byte count of the following data
</t>
          <t hangText="type[2]">
           <vspace/>
               for kernel use
</t>
          <t hangText="dev[4]">
           <vspace/>
               for kernel use
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.type[1]">
           <vspace/>
               the type of the file (directory, etc.), represented as
               a bit vector corresponding to the high 8 bits of the
               file's mode word.
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.vers[4]">
           <vspace/>
               version number for given path
</t>
          <t hangText="qid.path[8]">
           <vspace/>
               the file server's unique identification for the file
</t>
          <t hangText="mode[4]">
           <vspace/>
               permissions and flags
</t>
          <t hangText="atime[4]">
           <vspace/>
               last access time
</t>
          <t hangText="mtime[4]">
           <vspace/>
               last modification time
</t>
          <t hangText="length[8]">
           <vspace/>
               length of file in bytes
</t>
          <t hangText="name[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               file name; must be / if the file is the root directory
               of the server
</t>
          <t hangText="uid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               owner name
</t>
          <t hangText="gid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               group name
</t>
          <t hangText="muid[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               name of the user who last modified the file
</t>
          <t hangText="extension[ s ]">
           <vspace/>
               For use by the UNIX extension to store data about
	       special files (links, devices, pipes, etc.)
</t>
          <t hangText="n_uid[4]">
           <vspace/>
               numeric id of the user who owns the file
</t>
          <t hangText="n_gid[4]">
           <vspace/>
               numeric id of the group associated with the file
</t>
          <t hangText="n_muid[4]">
           <vspace/>
               numeric id of the user who last modified the file
</t>

         </list>
        </t>
       </list>
      </t>
      <t><vspace/>
	The n_uid, n_gid, and n_muid are numeric hints that clients
	may use to map numeric ids when a string to numeric id mapping
	facility is not available.
      </t>
      <t><vspace/>
	extension[s] is a string describing special files, depending on the
	mode bit.  For DSYMLINK files, the string is the target of the link.
	For DMDEVICE files, the string is "b 1 2" for a block device with 
	major 1, minor 2.   For normal files, this string is empty.
      </t>
      </list>
      </t>
   </section>
</section>

  <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>TODO: Talk about specific security considerations of 9P under
   UNIX, specifically about the different auth models <xref target="P9SEC" /></t>
  </section>
  <section title="Protocol Definition Differences">
<figure>
<artwork>
/* permissions */
enum {
        DMDIR =            0x80000000,
        DMAPPEND =         0x40000000,
        DMEXCL =           0x20000000,
        DMMOUNT =          0x10000000,
        DMAUTH =           0x08000000,
        DMTMP =            0x04000000,
        DMSYMLINK =        0x02000000,
        /* 9P2000.u extensions */
        DMDEVICE =         0x00800000,
        DMNAMEDPIPE =      0x00200000,
        DMSOCKET =         0x00100000,
        DMSETUID =         0x00080000,
        DMSETGID =         0x00040000,
};

/* qid.types */
enum {
        QTDIR =            0x80,
        QTAPPEND =         0x40,
        QTEXCL =           0x20,
        QTMOUNT =          0x10,
        QTAUTH =           0x08,
        QTTMP =	           0x04,
        QTLINK =           0x02,
        QTFILE =           0x00,
};
struct v9fs_stat {
        uint16_t size;
        uint16_t type;
        uint32_t dev;
        struct v9fs_qid qid;
        uint32_t mode;
        uint32_t atime;
        uint32_t mtime;
        uint64_t length;
        char *name;
        char *uid;
        char *gid;
        char *muid;
/* 9p2000.u extensions */
        char *extension;
        uint32_t n_uid;
        uint32_t n_gid;
        uint32_t n_muid;
     
        char data[0];
};

struct Rerror {
        char *error;
        uint32_t errno;         /* 9p2000.u extension */
};
</artwork>
</figure>
  </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
  <references title="Normative References">
		<reference anchor="PLAN9" target="http://plan9.bell-labs.com/plan9">
    <front>
     <title>Plan 9 Home Page</title>
     <author initials="" surname="Lucent Technologies" fullname="Lucent Technolgoies">
      <organization/>
     </author>
    </front>
   </reference>
   <reference anchor="P9SEC" target="http://plan9.bell-labs.com/sys/doc/auth.html">
    <front>
     <title>Security in Plan 9</title>
     <author initials="R.C." surname="Cox" fullname="Russ Cox">
      <organization>
				MIT LCS
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="E.G." surname="Grosse" fullname="Eric Grosse">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="R.P." surname="Pike" fullname="Rob Pike">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="D.P." surname="Presotto" fullname="Dave Presotto">
      <organization>
				Avaya Labs and Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <author initials="S.Q." surname="Quinlan" fullname="Sean Quinlan">
      <organization>
				Bell Labs
			 </organization>
     </author>
     <date year="2002" />
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="Proceedings" value="of the Usenix Security Symposium" />
   </reference>
  </references>
  <section title="Acknowledgements">
<t>
The 9P2000.u protocol extensions evolved out of contributions from a
number of people including:
<list>
	<t>Abhishek Kilkarni</t>
	<t>Russ Cox</t>
	<t>Lachester Ionkov</t>
	<t>Ron Minnich</t>
	<t>Andrey Mirtchoviski</t>
	<t>Rob Pike</t>
	<t>Eric Van Hensbergen</t>
	<t>Uriel (Contentious Objector)</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
The 9P protocol was the result of work done by the Computing Science
Research Center of AT&T Bell Labs (now a part of Lucent Technologies) and in
particular:
<list>
     <t>
Rob Pike</t>
     <t>
Dave Presotto</t>
     <t>
Sape Mullender</t>
     <t>
Ken Thompson</t>
    <t>
Russ Cox
</t>
    </list>
   </t>
  </section>
  <section title="Copyright">
   <t>
  This specification is derrived from the Plan 9 Documentation and Manual Pages.
  The source material is
  Copyright (C) 2003, Lucent Technologies Inc.  and others.  All Rights Reserved.
  </t>
   <t>
  Extensions to the original source material are Copyright (C) 2005, the authors
  of this document (as specified in Authors List in the References section).
  </t>
  </section>
 </back>
</rfc>
